# STEFANO CASTRO TOGNINI

Oak Ridge National Laboratory

@ togninis@ornl.gov

+1 (865) 341 0453

stognini

in stognini

I have a Ph.D. in Physics, focused in High Energy Physics (HEP). Currently a Research Associate at Oak Ridge National Laboratory mainly working on *Celeritas*, a GPU-based HEP Monte Carlo particle transport code for the DOE Exascale Computing Project. In the past I was a collaborator working on two experiments known as MINOS and NOvA, managed by Fermi National Accelerator Laboratory (Fermilab). These are long-term multi-million dollar endeavors built to understand the nature of neutrinos and answer fundamental questions related to astrophysics, dark matter, and more. My 7+ years of experience, including spending at least 1 year based at Fermilab and Argonne National Laboratory working with diversified teams, led to many published data analyses, all developed using C++, Python, ROOT, shell scripting, massive parallel computing, and Monte Carlo simulations. Software development is managed using version control (GIT/SVN), allied with automated code referencing (Doxygen). Production of technical documentation is routinely done. Finally, I have experience with teaching at undergraduate level, mentoring graduate students, presenting findings at international conferences, as well as participating in science outreach events.

#### PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

#### Research Associate

HPC Methods for Nuclear Applications Group Nuclear Energy and Fuel Cycle Division Oak Ridge National Laboratory

# 2019 - Present

Oak Ridge (TN), U.S.

#### **COLLABORATIONS**

Celeritas Project

github.com/celeritas-project

## 2020 - Present

**♀** ORNL

Core member of the Celeritas development team.

#### **URL Muon Detector Project**

## 2020 - Present

• ORNL

Core team member involved with all stages of the project: detector design, simulation, commissioning, deployment, and analysis.

### **NO** $\nu$ **A Experiment**

novaexperiment.fnal.gov

**#** 2013 − 2018

- **♀** Fermilab / ANL / UFG
- Leading author of a published data analysis: PRD 99 122004.
- Integrated a Monte Carlo package with the Fermilab computing framework that is being used by two other experiments at Fermilab and CERN.
- Commissioned/maintained a Remote Operation Center (ROC) at UFG.
- Hardware work that consisted in testing the quality of Avalanche Photo Diodes before being installed in the NO $\nu$ A Near Detector.

## **MINOS Experiment**

www-numi.fnal.gov

## 2011 - Present

- **♀** Fermilab / ANL / UFG
- Worked in 2 published data analyses: PRD 91 112006 / PRD 93 052017.
- Wrote documentation for commissioning and certifying ROCs.
- Installed and maintained the MINOS Main Operation Center at Fermilab.
- Built, documented, and maintained a MINOS ROC at UFG.

#### SCIENTIFIC PUBLICATIONS

#### SOFT SKILLS

Teaching (3 yrs) Mentoring (4 yrs)

Scientific outreach Public speaking

Portuguese (native)
English
Italian

## **HARD SKILLS**

French

Technical skills Parallel computing Data structuring Data analysis Monte Carlo simulation **Programming & scripting languages** C/C++ Python SQL Shell PT-X Frameworks, libraries, databases, & tools Fermilab ART Framework **GIT** Geant4 ROOT **CORSIKA TORQUE** Doxygen

#### **EDUCATION**

Ph.D. in Physics – High Energy Physics

## Federal University of Goias

Funding: CAPES, CNPq, ANL

**#** 2012 − 2018

**♀** Goiania (GO), Brazil

**DOE** OSTI www.osti.gov/biblio/1468447 iNSPIRE HEP inspirehep.net/record/1692030

M.Sc. in Physics - High Energy Physics

## **Federal University of Goias**

Funding: CAPES, Fermilab

**∰** 2010 − 2012

♥ Goiania (GO), Brazil

B.Sc. in Physics

## **Federal University of Goias**

**#** 2005 − 2010

♀ Goiania (GO), Brazil